Guide to the Carol Bleier Research Files for "Tradition in Transition", 1901-2000 UA.90.29.12
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Carol Bleier Research Files for "Tradition in Transition"
1998-1999
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Bleier, Carol
UA.90.29.12
3.75 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
Carol Bleier wrote a history of the School of Information Sciences in 2000. The book was called Tradition in Transition and it chronicled the years of 1901-2000, from when the library school began at Carnegie Institute of Technology to its current incarnation as a graduate school within the University of Pittsburgh. This collection documents the resources that Bleier used in writing the book which are photocopies of material from the Archives Service Center, 1901-2000.
Biography
A freelance writer, researcher, and public relations specialist, Carol Bleier is the author of three books, which include: To Good Health and Life: L'Chaim: A History of Montefiore Hospital of Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 1898-1990 (co-written with Lu Donnelly and Samuel P. Granowitz); Ketchum Spirit: A History of Ketchum Communications Inc. (with Lu Donnelly); and her most recent publication, a history of the University of Pittsburgh's School of Information Sciences entitled, Tradition in Transition: A History of the School of Information Sciences, University of Pittsburgh: 100th Anniversary 1901--2001. Ms. Bleier has a master's degree from the School of Information Sciences, University of Pittsburgh.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection contains photocopied source materials for Tradition in Transition, a detailed history of the School of Information Sciences at the University of Pittsburgh, covering the first 100 years of the school. Though much of the material consists of photocopies from books, journals, newspapers, and primary source materials held by the University Archives, it is grouped together for the unique purpose of the writing of this book, providing an example of the process used and the research materials required to write an institutional history.
This collection contains four series. Series I. contains resource materials and research notes. Series II. contains faculty and alumni profiles and oral histories. Series III. contains Katz Graduate School of Business booklets and brochures. Series IV. contains School of Library and Information Sciences booklets and brochures.
Access Restrictions
Restrictions on oral histories that do not have release forms.
Acquisition Information
Deposited by the School of Information Sciences in 1999.
Existence and Location of Copies
This collection consists of photocopies of materials housed in many of the collections at the Archives Service Center, particularly University Archives.
Previous Citation
Carol Bleier Research Files for "Tradition in Transition", 1901-2000, UA.90.29.12, University Archives, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Collection of Carol Bleier, Tradition in Transition, 1998-1999, RG 90/29, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
University of Pittsburgh; Library schools -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- History; Library education -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- History; University of Pittsburgh. School of Information Sciences -- History; Bleier, Carol. Tradition in Transition
- Resource Materials and Author's Notes, 1901-2000; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Series I contains resource materials and author's notes. Many of the items within the folders are photocopies from original archival documents or published works. Some of the materials are original publications. The folder titles that begin at 1901-1929 and span to 2000, correspond directly with the chronological structure of Carol Bleier's book, Tradition in Transition. The folder titles include predominant dates and may also contain some undated material.
  - Airport, 1988-1992 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - AFL-CIO, 1989-1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Butler County, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - High Technology, 1986-1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Iron and Steel Industry, 1982-1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Papercraft Story, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Code of Ethics - Accounting, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Greensburg Campus, 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - School of Law - University of Pittsburgh, 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1901-1929 (Box 1, Folder 10-14)
  - 1930s (Box 1, Folder 15-18)
  - 1940s (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1950s (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - The Lancour Years, 1962-1974 (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
  - The Lancour Years Correspondence, 1962-1974 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - The Frank Sessa Years, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - The Galvin Years, 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 25-28)
  - The Galvin Years, 1978-1986 (Box 1, Folder 29-33)
  - The Galvin Years Notes, no date (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - The Galvin Years, Correspondence, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - The Carbo Years Notes, 1989-2000 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - The Carbo Years, Correspondence, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - The Carbo Years, 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 38-40)
  - The Carbo Years, 1990-2000 (Box 1, Folder 41-45)
  - Copy of Manuscript, 172 pages, no date (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Copy of Manuscript, no date (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Profiles and Oral Histories, 1901-2000; II.
  Series II contains profiles and oral histories. Profiles exist for all of the people listed below, as well as subject listings. However, there are only oral histories for some and are found in the same folder as the profiles material. The materials within each folder correspond to specific one page profiles in Carol Bleier's book.
  - Misc. Profiles (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - First Faculty (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Prof. Almagno (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Edwin Anderson (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Beta Phi Mu (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Sarah Bogle (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Casimir Barkowski (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Toni Carbo (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Andrew Carnegie (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Richard Cox (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Jay Daily (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Ellen Detlefsen (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Anthony Debons (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Sara Fine (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Thomas Galvin (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Margaret Hodges (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Norman Horrocks (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Vivian Davidson Hewitt (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Dr. Phil Immroth (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - E.J. Josey (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Allen Kent (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Maggie Kimmel (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Harold Lancour (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Ida Mary Lewis (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Martha Manheimer (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Ralph Munn (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Margaret McEldery (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Dr. William Nasri (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Elizabeth Nesbitt (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Nesbitt Room (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Frances Jenkins Olcott (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Patrick Penland (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Patrick Pond (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Virginia Powell (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Sister Jane Scully (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Don Shiry (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Frank Sessa (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Jim Williams (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Esther Blanche Woolls (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Wendall Wray (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Katz School Booklets and Brochures, 1960-1999; III.
  Series III contains booklets and brochures created by the Katz Graduate School of Business. The Katz School and the School of Information Science have some classes that correspond so that students may cross-register.
  - Advertising, 1980-1999 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Articles, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Directory of candidates, 1975-1999 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Doctoral Student Manual, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Faculty Manuals, 1971-1975 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Graduation Catalogs, 1988-1999 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - In the News, 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Publications, 1988-1999 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Reports, 1960-1991 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Self Study for the Accreditation by the American Assembly of Collegiate Schools, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Undergraduate Business Program at Johnstown Campus, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- School of Library and Information Sciences Booklets and Brochures, 1966-2001; IV.
  Series IV contains booklets and brochures created by the Library School and the School of Information Sciences.
  - LIS Alumni Association Newsletter, 1982-2000 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Course Catalogs and Bulletins, 1982-1993 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Dalhousie University News, January 22, 1971, 1982-2000 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Faculty and Staff Directory, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - SIS Faculty Directories, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - SIS Faculty Directories, 1991-1994 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Lecture Flyers, 1983-1996 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Library Manuals, 1966-1970 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Promotional Materials, 1980-2000 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Sara Fine Institute, 2000-2001 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - SLIS Publications, 1987-2000 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - School Librarians' Institute, 1992-1996 (Box 3, Folder 23)